Marguerite Harris Papers
Marguerite Harris Papers
1901-1978
Harris, Marguerite.
2.25 linear ft.
Spanning 1901 to 1978, the Marguerite Harris Papers comprises correspondence, writings, and memorabilia of the American avant-garde poet and editor (1898 or 9-1978). An active member of the Poetry Society of America, Marguerite Harris bridged the gap between two generations of poets: the Imagist and Surrealist writers, and the Beats. The collection not only reflects her professional career, but also offers a unique insight into the life and work of a number of young poets of the 1950s, 60s and 70s.
149038
Biographical History
American poet and editor (1898 or 9-1978).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Composed of incoming letters and outgoing carbons from 1955 through 1977, the Correspondence/Subject Files (Boxes 1-2) forms the bulk of the collection. Much of the correspondence centers around Harris' work as an organizer of poetry readings for Dr. Generosity's Poetry Pub and the Woodstock Poetry Festival, and as the editor of a number of poetry anthologies, including Emily Dickinson: Letters from the World (1970), Loves, etc. (1973), and A Tumult for John Berryman (1976). Correspondence of greatest depth and duration includes that with Helen Adam, Carol Berge, James Clifford, Richard Eberhart, Isabella Gardner, Alonzo Gibbs, William Kinter, Wendell Metzger, Joe Rosenblatt, and the Poetry Society of America. Other correspondents include Conrad Aiken, Daisy Aldan, Margaret Atwood, Robert Bly, Louise Bogan, William Bronk, Andrei Codrescu, Robert Creeley, Diane Di Prima, John Duffy, Theodore Enslin, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Barbara Guest, Langston Hughes, David Ignatow, Colette Inez, Jackson Mac Low, William Meredith, Marianne Moore, Walter Quirt, Margaret Randall, William Safire, Stevie Smith, William Stafford, Gerd Stern, May Swenson, Eve Triem, Diane Wakoski, Jonathan Williams, Celeste Turner Wright, and Jean Wrolson. In addition, there is a small amount of family correspondence.
Anthology and periodical appearances, books, letters to editors, speeches, and manuscript and published poems, many of which appeared in Harris' The Risk of the Vine (1965), A Reconciling of Rivers (1972), and Time of the Playback (1977), constitute Writings (Boxes 3-4). Arranged by title, manuscript poems (occasionally interspersed with tear sheets) include holograph and typed worksheets indicating numerous revisions. Several periodical issues and anthologies in which Marguerite Harris' work appears have been retained with the collection, while others have been integrated with the Library's rare book collections.
Memorabilia (Box 5) encompasses artwork for one of Harris' poetry projects, photographs, printed material, and manuscript and published reviews. Printed material includes books, bulletins of the Poetry Society of America, clippings about both Harris and the poetry readings she organized, and programs.
Subject and Genre Headings
Women Authors; Radicalism; Literature -- American Poetry; Literature -- American Fiction; Adam, Helen, 1909-1993.; Aiken, Conrad, 1889-1973.; Aldan, Daisy.; Atwood, Margaret.; Bergé, Carol, 1928-2006.; Bly, Robert.; Bogan, Louise, 1897-1970.; Bronk, William.; Clifford, James L. (James Lowry), 1901-1978.; Codrescu, Andrei, 1946-; Creeley, Robert, 1926-2005.; Di Prima, Diane.; Duffy, John.; Eberhart, Richard, 1904-2005.; Enslin, Theodore.; Ferlinghetti, Lawrence.; Gardner, Isabella.; Gibbs, Alonzo, 1915-; Guest, Barbara.; Harris, Marguerite.; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967.; Ignatow, David, 1914-1997.; Inez, Colette.; Kinter, William Lewis, 1915-; Mac Low, Jackson.; Meredith, William, 1919-; Metzger, Wendell.; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972.; Quirt, Walter, 1902-1968.; Randall, Margaret, 1936-; Rosenblatt, Joe, 1933-; Safire, William, 1929-2009.; Smith, Stevie, 1902-1971.; Stafford, William, 1914-1993.; Stern, Gerd.; Swenson, May.; Triem, Eve, 1902-1992.; Wakoski, Diane.; Williams, Jonathan, 1929-2008.; Wright, Celeste Turner.; Wrolson, Jean.; Poetry Society of America.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Authors, American.; Bohemianism -- United States.; Dr. Generosity's Poetry Pub (New York, N.Y.); Literature, Experimental.; Poetry, Modern -- 20th century.; Poets, American.; Women editors -- United States.; Women poets, American.; Woodstock Poetry Festival (Woodstock, N.Y.); Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Photographs.; Poems.; Editors.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Marguerite Harris, 1966-1977.
Inventory
- Correspondence/Subject Files
  - Biographical material/Inventory (Box 1)
  - Adam, Helen, 1970-1977; undated (Box 1)
  - Aiken, Conrad, 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - Aldan, Daisy, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Anderson, Chester G., 1973 (Box 1)
  - Ansley, Delight, 1964; undated (Box 1)
  - Antin, Eleanor, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Arizona State University, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Atheneum Publishers, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Atwood, Margaret, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Berge, Carol, 1971-1977; undated (Box 1)
  - Bishop, Elizabeth, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Bly, Robert and Carol, 1960-1974; undated (Box 1)
  - Bogan, Louise, 1956-1968 (Box 1)
  - Books Abroad, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Bornstein, Diane, 1975-1976; undated (Box 1)
  - Braymer, Nan, undated (Box 1)
  - Bronk, William, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Browne, Michael Dennis, 1973; undated (Box 1)
  - Buchman, Marion, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Buckingham, Walter S., undated (Box 1)
  - Bullock, Marie, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Caraher-Manning, Doreen, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Casement, Douglas, See The Sparrow
  - Choice Magazine, See Kessler, Milton
  - Clifford, James L. and Virginia, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Codrescu, Andrei, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Cohen, Joe, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Cohen, William Howard, undated (Box 1)
  - Congdon, Kirby, 1971; 1974 (Box 1)
  - Coolidge, Clark, undated (Box 1)
  - Corman, Cid, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Coudert, Jo, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Counter/Measures, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Creeley, Robert, 1961-1970 (Box 1)
  - Cunningham, John Vincent, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Damascus Road, 1970; 1975 (Box 1)
  - Danzig, Allan, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Day, Wesley, undated (Box 1)
  - Deitz, Paula, See The Hudson Review
  - Desy, Peter, undated (Box 1)
  - Diederich, Lynn - cover designs, undated (Box 1)
  - Di Prima, Diane, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Dr. Generosity's Poetry Pub (New York, N.Y.), 1970-1975; undated (Box 1)
  - Dorn, Alfred, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Dragonette, Ree, 1963; 1971 (Box 1)
  - Duffy, John, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Eaton, Charles Edward, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Eberhart, Richard, 1967-1969; undated (Box 1)
  - Elizabeth Press, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Emily Dickinson Bulletin, See Morey, Frederick L.
  - Enslin, Theodore, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Enzenberger, Hans Magnus, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Farrar, Straus & Giroux, Inc., 1966-1975 (Box 1)
  - Ferlinghetti, Lawrence, 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Ferrell, Wilfred A., 1975 (Box 1)
  - Flute, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Forum (University of Houston), 1962 (Box 1)
  - Friedlaender, Marc, See Atheneum Publishers
  - Gardner, Isabella, 1954-1976; undated (Box 1)
  - Gibbs, Alonzo, 1970-1977; undated (Box 1)
  - Gill, John, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Glaze, Andrew, 1964-1973; undated (Box 1)
  - Goodman, Paul, undated (Box 1)
  - Griffith, E. V., See Poetry Now
  - Gross, Ronald, undated (Box 1)
  - Guest, Barbara, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Hanna, Charles Shahoud, See Damascus Road
  - Hernandez, Julio (pseudonym), See Codrescu, Andrei
  - Hershon, Robert, undated (Box 1)
  - Hollander, John, undated (Box 1)
  - House of Anansi Press, See Atwood, Margaret
  - The Hudson Review, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Hughes, Langston, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Hunting, Constance, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Ignatow, David, 1964; 1973 (Box 1)
  - Inez, Colette, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Jargon Books, See Williams, Jonathan
  - Jewish Dialog, See Rosenblatt, Joe
  - Kennedy, X. J., See Counter/Measures
  - Kessler, Milton, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Kinter, William, 1964-1975; undated (Box 1)
  - Koch, Kenneth, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Kray, Elizabeth, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Krenis, Linda, See The New York Quarterly
  - Kroll, Ernest, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Kunitz, Stanley, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Lachman, Vera, undated (Box 2)
  - Lezak, Iris, undated (Box 2)
  - Lieberman, Elias, 1963-1965 (Box 2)
  - Lorenz, Konrad, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Lourie, Dick, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Lowenfels, Walter, 1961; 1964 (Box 2)
  - McCord, Howard, 1972 (Box 2)
  - McCullough, Frances Monson, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Mac Low, Jackson, 1963-1973 (Box 2)
  - Mally, Louise, undated (Box 2)
  - Martin, Herbert, 1964; undated (Box 2)
  - Matson, Clive, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Matthews, William, 1971; 1975 (Box 2)
  - Mayo, Edward L., 1966 (Box 2)
  - Mele, Frank, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Meredith, William, 1973-1976; undated (Box 2)
  - Merwin, William Stanley, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Metzger, Wendell, 1969-1971; undated (Box 2)
  - Meyer, Gerard Previn, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Montgomery, George, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Moore, Marianne, 1958-1972; undated (Box 2)
  - Morey, Frederick L., 1970; undated (Box 2)
  - Morgan, Frederick, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Moss, Howard, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Mulch, 1972 (Box 2)
  - The Nation, 1972-1975 (Box 2)
  - New York Public Library, 1965-1971 (Box 2)
  - The New York Quarterly, 1971 (Box 2)
  - The New York Times, 1970-1975 (Box 2)
  - Newton, Violette, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Norris, Ken, undated (Box 2)
  - North, Charles, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Oden, Gloria C., 1973; 1975 (Box 2)
  - Olson, Toby, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Oppen, George, undated (Box 2)
  - Owens, Rochelle, undated (Box 2)
  - Packard, William, See The New York Quarterly
  - Pennant, Edmund, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - Phelps, Donald, 1975; undated (Box 2)
  - Poetry Now, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
  - Poetry Society of America, 1956-1977; undated (Box 2)
  - Poets and Writers (New York, N.Y.), 1972-1977; undated (Box 2)
  - Polgar, Antoine J., 1964 (Box 2)
  - Pottle, Frederick, 1962-1975 (Box 2)
  - Prising, Robin, 1965-1977 (Box 2)
  - Quarterly Review of Literature, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Quasha, George, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Quirt, Walter and Eleanor, 1967; undated (Box 2)
  - Randall, Margaret, 1964-1972; undated (Box 2)
  - Redgrove, Peter, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Regan, Robert, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Roseliep, Raymond, 1966-1974 (Box 2)
  - Rosenblatt, Joe, 1964-1976; undated (Box 2)
  - Rosenthal, Macha L., 1963 (Box 2)
  - Ross, David, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  - Rosten, Norman, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Rudolf, Anthony, undated (Box 2)
  - Safire, William, undated (Box 2)
  - Sanders, Ed, 1965-1975 (Box 2)
  - Schulman, Grace, 1977; undated (Box 2)
  - Shetline, Leonard, undated (Box 2)
  - Silverman, Herschel, 1964-1970; undated (Box 2)
  - Simmons, Ted, undated (Box 2)
  - Simpson, Peter L., undated (Box 2)
  - Smith, Jared, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Smith, Stevie, 1964-1968; undated (Box 2)
  - The Sparrow, undated (Box 2)
  - Stafford, William, 1972-1977 (Box 2)
  - Stepanchev, Stephen, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Stern, Gerd, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Strachan, William, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Sutherland, Edwin, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Swarts, William, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Swenson, May, undated (Box 2)
  - Thomas, Ronald Stuart, undated (Box 2)
  - Triem, Eve, 1967-1971 (Box 2)
  - Turco, Lewis, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Tusiani, Joseph, 1966 (Box 2)
  - University of Pittsburgh Press, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Valentine, Jean, undated (Box 2)
  - Vas Dias, Robert, See Mulch
  - Wade, John Stevens, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Wakoski, Diane, 1966-1976; undated (Box 2)
  - Wallenstein, Barry, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Warnke, Frank J., 1966 (Box 2)
  - Weil, J. L., See Elizabeth Press
  - Weiss, Theodore, See Quarterly Review of Literature
  - Wesleyan University Press, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Wheelock, John Hall, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Widdemer, Margaret, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Wieners, John, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Wild, Peter, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Williams, Jonathan, 1960; 1964 (Box 2)
  - Williams, Oscar, undated (Box 2)
  - Woodstock Times, 1975; 1977 (Box 2)
  - Wormwood Review, See Montgomery, George
  - Wright, Celeste Turner, 1967; 1970 (Box 2)
  - Wrolsen, Jean, 1972; 1976 (Box 2)
  - The Yale Literary Magazine, 1956-1966 (Box 2)
  - Young, Al, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Zimmer, Honora M. (Sister), 1971 (Box 2)
  - Zimmer, Paul, See University of Pittsburgh Press
  - Family correspondence, 1961-1970; undated (Box 2)
  - Unidentified correspondence (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Anthology appearances
    - The Golden Year, 1960 (Box 3)
    - Art and the Craftsman, 1961 (Box 3)
    - A Garland for Dylan Thomas, 1963 (Box 3)
    - The Venice Poetry Company Presents, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Books
    - Coffee House Crumbs, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Loves, etc., 1973; edited by Marguerite Harris (Box 3)
    - Time of the playback, 1975; typescript; includes letter from Harris to Merrill Leffler (publisher) and from William Stafford to Marguerite Harris (Box 3)
  - Letters to editors, 1973-1976; undated (Box 3)
  - Periodical appearances
    - The Yale Literary Magazine v. 122, no. 2, 1954 (Box 3)
    - Wisconsin Poetry Magazine v. 3, no. 6, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Forum (University of Houston) v. 3, no. 5, 1960 (Box 3)
    - The Nation v. 195, no. 4, 1962 (Box 3)
    - El Corno Emplumado/The Plumed Horn no. 6, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Forum (University of Houston) v. 4, no. 2 (Box 3)
    - Joglars v. 1, no. 2, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Marrahwanna Quarterly no. 2 (Box 4)
    - Wormwood Review v. 5, no. 1, 1965 (Box 4)
    - The Yale Literary Magazine v. 134, no. 5, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Damascus Road no. 3, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Wormwood Review v. 9, no. 2, 1969 (Box 4)
    - The New York Quarterly no. 7, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Damascus Road no. 4, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Dialog Passover Hymn Anthology v. 3 (Box 4)
    - 13th Moon v. 1, no. 2, 1974 (Box 4)
    - Cross Country no. 1, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Street Magazine v. 2, no. 2, 1976 (Box 4)
    - For Now no. 14, undated (Box 4)
  - Poetry (by title), 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Speeches, 1971; undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4)
- Memorabilia
  - Artwork for Emily Dickinson: Letters from the World, original drawings (Box 5)
  - Photographs, 1901-1971; undated (Box 5)
  - "Poetry Party", 1955 (Box 5)
  - Printed material
    - Books
      - O to Be a Dragon / Marianne Moore (Box 5)
      - Signals (Box 5)
    - Bulletins
      - Poetry Society of America, 1961-1970 (Box 5)
    - Clippings
      - About Marguerite Harris, 1935-1978 (Box 5)
      - Poetry readings (Box 5)
    - Programs, 1975; 1977 (Box 5)
    - Publicity
      - Poetry readings (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Reviews, manuscript and published (Box 5)
    - Miscellany (Box 5)